<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good newes for England, or, Comfortable tydings from Ireland to all true hearted Protestants being a real relation of how Sir Simon Harcourt, Sergeant Major Berry, and Captian Paramore, with the joint assistance of divers other Protestants, obtained a famous victory over the rebels at Kildare : as also how the Lord Dulon was grievously wounded, and a kinsman of his taken prisoner, with the number of those that were slain on each side / sent ... by Alderman Guy , his son, of Bristol, to Sir Richard Grenvile, Mar. 10.</title>
            <author>Guy, William, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08153384</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08153384</idno>
            <idno type="VID">204218</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23801)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204218)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1230:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good newes for England, or, Comfortable tydings from Ireland to all true hearted Protestants being a real relation of how Sir Simon Harcourt, Sergeant Major Berry, and Captian Paramore, with the joint assistance of divers other Protestants, obtained a famous victory over the rebels at Kildare : as also how the Lord Dulon was grievously wounded, and a kinsman of his taken prisoner, with the number of those that were slain on each side / sent ... by Alderman Guy , his son, of Bristol, to Sir Richard Grenvile, Mar. 10.</title>
                  <author>Guy, William, 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Grenville, Richard, Sir, 1600-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Wil. Guy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204218:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204218:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204218:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOOD NEWES <hi>FOR</hi> ENGLAND: OR, Comfortable Tydings from Ireland, to all true hearted Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BEING</hi> A REAL RELATION HOW SIR <hi>Simon Harcourt,</hi> Sergeant Major <hi>Berry,</hi> and Captain <hi>Paramore,</hi> with the joint Aſſiſtance of divers other Proteſtants, obtained a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Victory over the Rebels at <hi>Kildare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo how the Lord <hi>Dulon</hi> was grievouſly wounded, and a Kinſman of his taken priſoner, with the number of thoſe that were ſlain on each ſide.</p>
            <p>Sent from the Engliſh Quarters at <hi>Lyons,</hi> within four miles of <hi>Dublin</hi> by Alderman <hi>Guy</hi> his Son of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> Cornet to Sir <hi>Richard Grenvile,</hi> Mar. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for ROBERT WOOD, 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:204218:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204218:3"/>
            <head>THE PROTESTANTS LAST LAST VICTORY OVER FHE REBELS IN <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>DEAR BROTHER:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received your Letter of the 10. of Febr. but had never opportunity or leaſure to recommend my true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to you, untill this fit occaſion prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; for we have bin ſo buſied upon ſtrict duty ever ſince, that we have had ſcarce time to eat our ſmall victuals we get, for the Rogues are up in every place about us, ſo that we are every day upon ſome march or ſervice; but this Bearer hath faithfully promiſed to deliver this with his own hands unto you: and
<pb facs="tcp:204218:4"/>therfore I will to ſatisfie your requeſt, relate to you ſuch <hi>Occurrents,</hi> and paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as have lately fallen out here; for my own part, I have not bin well ever ſince our buſineſſe at <hi>Aſhinhanon,</hi> by means of a fall I got homewards.</p>
            <p>Yet on monday morning I made a ſhift to get to Horſe, and marcht with our troop towards <hi>Kildare;</hi> upon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a skirmiſh at <hi>Lunderſton</hi> between the Rebels and Lieutenant Col. <hi>Hurcliffi</hi> where the Rebels were put to ſlight, and thereupon the L. <hi>Dulon</hi> removed from <hi>Caterlaff,</hi> and came towards <hi>Woodſtocke,</hi> that night we lay at <hi>Clanmor,</hi> and the Rebels at <hi>Bolton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Tueſday morning we had a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Sir <hi>Simon Harcourt</hi> by three a clock to march towards <hi>Kildare,</hi> we were in all 180. Horſe, and 1300 foot, at our going forth, and by 8. of the clock in the morning we had intelligence by the people of our Party, that the Rebels had marched all night, and were in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at leaſt 6000. horſe and foot, which
<pb facs="tcp:204218:4"/>made us ſomwhat pauſe upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and at a place of advantage (within a mile of <hi>Kildare</hi>) to make a ſtand.</p>
            <p>But within half an hour, we had News that <hi>Serieant Maior Berrie,</hi> and Captain <hi>Parramore</hi> were within an hours march of us and made all the haſt they could from their quarters towards us, with their Companies, and two pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ordnance, which we found to be true, which put a great deal of courage unto us, and ſo wee marcht onwards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Kildare,</hi> where we underſtood the Rebels were at <hi>Water,</hi> a little Town four miles off, and that they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching themſelves there.</p>
            <p>Which to prevent, we made all the haſte we could to them, and about four in the Afternoon we perceived them.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>MARRO</hi> was the firſt Troop appointed to fall on, and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieant Maior Berrie</hi> of the Foot, which was bravely ſeconded by all our Forces there, playing againſt them couragiouſly
<pb facs="tcp:204218:5"/>But the ſport laſted not above half an hour before a great ſtorm of Raign fell on us, which hindered our play, and the Rebels retreated into a wood, near <hi>Water</hi> Town, where they reſted untill 7. a clock at night; at which time our ſire-locks gave them ſuch a ſalutation, that being ſeconded by the reſt of our Forces, they were enforced to leave the wood, and fly towards <hi>Woodſtock,</hi> which gave us ſuch contentment, that we failed not to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them, untill they came to <hi>Bernee,</hi> where we fell upon their Carriages, and proviſion, Sir <hi>Richard Grenvile</hi> took a Kinſman of the Lord <hi>Dulons</hi> with his own hand, in the Chaſe we alſo took 35 of their horſe, amongſt whom was one Lieutenant <hi>Fitz-James,</hi> whoſe horſe and furniture came to my lot; we alſo took three pieces of Iron Ordinance, four wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons of Ammunition, ſeven waggons of Bread, Cheeſe, and Butter (which made us very merry) 700. Cattell. 3000. ſheep, and above 200. Swine, with above 400. mens Armes; with which we bravely
<pb facs="tcp:204218:5"/>marcht towards <hi>Kildare</hi> where we mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily cheer'd our bellies, and laſt night came home into our quarters.</p>
            <p>We loſt in all this ſervice about 97. men, amongſt whom was Lieutenant <hi>Cannock,</hi> and Captain <hi>Marroes</hi> Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, and of our own Company <hi>Will Parker,</hi> and the Cutler, and no more, <hi>Fitz-James</hi> ſaith, that the Lord <hi>Dulon</hi> received a ſhot in one of his thighs, and was in great danger, and that they loſt above 1000. men in the skirmiſh and flight, and ſome other News upon hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay I could write, but that I leave till the next conveniency, and to the Relation of Sir <hi>Richard</hi> his man, and deſire you to haſten him away to my Mother: for I cannot be quiet till I hear from her, pray if you come not over, let me hear from you at every opportunity, and what News at home, for we hear a 100. lyes.</p>
            <p>You ſhall not fail to receive Letters from me by every Poſt that comes from us, as long as I am able to write to you. Commend me to <hi>Edward Seamor,</hi> Mrs.
<pb facs="tcp:204218:6"/>
               <hi>Kate,</hi> and her Mother, and with my true reſpects commended to your ſelf. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to the protection of the higheſt, and will ever remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in what I may, <hi>WIL. GUY,</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>From <hi>Lyons,</hi> 
                  <date>Mar. 10. 1641.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:204218:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
